<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sharepoint on Stuart McColl</title>
    <link>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/tags/sharepoint/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sharepoint on Stuart McColl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 16:00:48 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://stuartmccoll.github.io/tags/sharepoint/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Attaching to list items with the Microsoft SharePoint REST API</title>
      <link>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/posts/2020-06-22-attaching-to-list-items-with-sharepoint-rest-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 16:00:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/posts/2020-06-22-attaching-to-list-items-with-sharepoint-rest-api/</guid>
      <description>In my last blog post I explained how to create list items with Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s legacy SharePoint REST API using Postman. This post builds on that work to attach a file to an existing list item.
 Assuming you&amp;rsquo;ve been following along, we have a SharePoint list with at least one item in it that we&amp;rsquo;ve created through a request sent from Postman to the Microsoft SharePoint REST API. The item we created will have been assigned an id within SharePoint.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating list items with the Microsoft SharePoint REST API</title>
      <link>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/posts/2020-06-18-creating-list-items-with-sharepoint-rest-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 19:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/posts/2020-06-18-creating-list-items-with-sharepoint-rest-api/</guid>
      <description>In my last blog post I explained how to authenticate requests to Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s legacy SharePoint REST API using Postman. This post builds on that work to store our access token as a Postman environment variable and to then send POST requests to the SharePoint REST API to create new items within an existing SharePoint list.
 If you were following along previously, the last thing we did was to request an access token to use in future requests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft SharePoint API Access with Postman</title>
      <link>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/posts/2020-06-16-sharepoint-api-authentication-with-postman/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 21:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stuartmccoll.github.io/posts/2020-06-16-sharepoint-api-authentication-with-postman/</guid>
      <description>Microsoft Graph API has largely superceded v1 of the SharePoint REST API for API-driven interaction with SharePoint online, but there are still a few things that you can&amp;rsquo;t do with it. For example, at the time of writing, it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to use Microsoft Graph API to add attachments to a list item, or retrieve attachments from an existing list item. The legacy SharePoint REST API does allow for this functionality.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>